Dr. M. Usman Magbool **Bhutta**

POSTDOCTORAL ASSOCIATE · COMPUTER VISION AND SENSING SYSTEMS (COVISS), ABE, UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA

1741 Museum Rd, 185, Gainesville, FL 32603, United States.

□+1 (352) 721-8879 | Susmanmaqbool@outlook.com | #usmanmaqbool.github.io | □ UsmanMaqbool

"Roboticist + Entrepreneur"

Summary.

I am interested in developing more effective problem-solving strategies for complex challenges and acquiring new technologies and tools as needed. I can describe myself as a dedicated individual with strengths in project management, market research, team building, proposal writing, and presentation skills. I have over 8 years of specialized experience in robotics research and development, as well as project management. I previously served as the co-founder and Chief Operating Officer of a startup company that provided indoor navigation services using visible light communication technology [Lisee Technology Corporation Limited Hong Kong]. I have also held a director position at Friends corporate technologies and introduced Dalocation.com, a dynamic real estate mapping platform. In 2018, HKUST organized the Campus Challenge @ HKUST Transportation event, which received over 80 proposals. My work was recognized with the Audience Award, which I received from HKUST President Wei Shyy. I have also presented the Lisee technology at the IET-YPEC held at the City University of Hong Kong. In 2018, our company received HK\$160,000 in funding support from the Proof-of-Concept Fund at HKUST. Furthermore, in 2019, we were awarded HK\$300,000 in funding from the Technology Start-up Support Scheme for Universities in Hong Kong. I have been involved in several other entrepreneurial ventures in the real estate, marketing, and automation sectors since 2011. I am a straightforward individual who is passionate about research and development and enjoys turning ideas into reality. My full profile is available at the URL (https://usmanmaqbool.github.io/).

Work Experience

Research (Computer Vision Technologies and Robotics System)

Computer Vision and Sensing Systems (COVISS) Lab, Department of Agricultural and Biological Engineering

UF, United States.

Postdoctoral Associate

Aug. 2023 - Present

- Supervisor: Prof. Henry Medeiros, Director of Computer Vision and Sensing Systems (COVISS) Lab, University of Florida UF, United States...
- Research in place recognition and gricultural robotics

C3 Robotics Laboratory (C3RL), Department of Mechanical and Automation Engineering

CUHK, Hong Kong.

Postdoctoral Research Fellow

May 2021 - Jun. 2023

- Supervisor: Prof. Darwin Lau, Director of C3 Robotics Laboratory (C3RL), The Chinese University of Hong Kong CUHK, Hong Kong...
- Research in place recognition, AR/VR and inspection robotics for construction

I'm working on several projects here

Place Recognition: Working on the light-weight representation of images and making better use of previously trained models.

AR/VR: Research in **AR/VR** Platform design, multi-agent mixed reality, assistive prosthetics for the handicapped persons, teleoperated robots, human-robot interaction.

Inspection: Deep learning based research for the robotic presurface inspection for the construction.

Multi-agent collaboration: For indoor vegetation and painting robotics application.

Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab, Robotics InstitutePhD

HKUST, HK

Sep 2016 - Feb 2021

- PhD Supervisor: Prof Ming Liu, Director of Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab (RAM-LAB)
- Research Contributions as First Author

Place Recognition: Our work makes a leap towards hierarchical deep learning-based place recognition for multiagent SLAM systems. We introduce a probabilistic layer to constrain the local representation along with the global representation of images. The global description of the pre-trained model and the local consistency introduced in our work enables the system to yield good performance at large-scale.

Development Using: MATLAB, Python, Jupyter, Nvidia CUDA, Docker, Deep learning, Matconvnet

Multi-Agent SLAM: I've produced Loop-box for the multi-Agent Direct SLAM Triggered by Single Loop Closure for Large scale semi dense 3D reconstruction /large-scale structure from motion. This work is accepted for publication in IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics (IF= 11+)..

Development using: C++ 11, ROS, OpenCV, OpenGV, Paraview, EVO, UGV, LSD-SLAM, Monocular Camera.

SLAM: I've worked mainly for the multi-agent SLAM system. To find the scale difference and excellent relative transformation between difference agents. I've produced PCR-Pro work. This work got best student paper finalist award at IEEE-CYBER 2018.

Development using: C++ 11, ROS, OpenCV, OpenGV, Paraview, EVO, Monocular Camera, Plotly

Automation (Inspection): For smartphone glass inspection, I've introduced Smart-Inspect work. This work is accepted in IROS 2020. The patent is also under-review in the US.

Development using: Python, Jupyter, Nvidia CUDA, K-Means, Docker, Machine learning (ML)

ETH Zürich. Switzerland.

Academic Guest Oct. 2019 - Mar. 2020

- Supervisor: Prof. Roland Siegwart, Director of Autonomous Systems Lab (ASL), ETH Zürich, Switzerland.
- Co-Supervisor: Dr. Cesar Dario Cadena Lerma, Senior Researcher at ASL, ETH Zürich, Switzerland.
- Research in Place Recognition: I've worked for making the better place recognition for the better scene understanding. Furthermore, I've also introduced light weight representation of key-frames for better channel utilization.

Development using: MATLAB, Python, Jupyter, Nvidia CUDA, Docker, Deep learning, Matconvnet

Department of Electronics

OAU. Pakistan

MPhil Candidate Mar. 2010 - Jun. 2012

- M.Phil. Supervisor: Prof Hasan Mahmood, Department of Electronics, QAU.
- Research in Image Processing (CNN): I've introduced CNN-based license plate recognition of Pakistani's Cars. This work has been published in IEEE-ICALIP 2014.

Industry and Entrepreneurship

Lisee Technology Corporation Limited

Central, HK

Jan 2018 - Jan 2021

- Won funding support for company | TSSSU Support HK\$ 300,000 (Jun 19 May 20).
- Indoor Navigation for Libray using Lisee Technology | PCF Support HK\$ 160,000 (Jun 18 May 19).

Friends Corporate Technologies

Islamabad, PK

Feb 2013 - Aug 2015

50+ Projects | Electronics/ Electrical Engineering, R&D, image processing, Web Applications Development, MVC Applications

Federal Government of Pakistan

Islamabad, PK

Scientific Officer May 2012 - Feb 2013

Electronics/ Electrical Engineering, R&D, image processing

Server4Sale, LLC

Islamabad, PK

PHP Developer Dec 2009 - Mar 2010

Php web application development for Joomla and Zend frameworks.

Academic

COO

Department of Computer Science

BZU-Sahiwal, Pakistan

Lecturer (Visiting) Feb 2016 - Jun 2016

Teaching MCS and BS-CS courses

Department of Physics

GPGC Sahiwal, Pakistan

Oct. 2015 - May. 2016

Teaching BS physics (Electronics related courses + Labs + Projects)

Department of Electronics

QAU, Pakistan

Aug. 2010 - Dec. 2010

'PHP Web Development' (a short course) offered in Department of Electronics, Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad, Pakistan.

Education

Ph.D. in Robotics and AI at RAM-LAB, Robotics Institute

HKUST, Hong Kong

Department of Electronic & Computer Engineering, The Hong Kong University of Science and Technology

Sep 2016 - Jun 2021

- Thesis: "Towards A Swift Multiagent SLAM System For Large-scale Robotics Applications", June 17, 2021
- PhD Supervisor: Prof Ming Liu, Director of Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab (RAM-LAB)
- Exchange Supervisor: Prof. Roland Siegwart, Director of Autonomous Systems Lab (ASL), ETH Zürich, Switzerland.
- Exchange Co-Supervisor: Dr. Cesar Dario Cadena Lerma, Senior Researcher at ASL, ETH Zürich, Switzerland.
- Got PEEF CCMS PhD scholarship from Pakistan and overseas research award (ORA).
- · Research: Multi-Agent SLAM System, Place Recognition, Autonomous Car and Deep Learning for automation industry. Hand on experience on RGB-D 3D recontruction, Multi-view stereo, python and C++ development experience, multi-threaded coding.3D mesh registration, paraview and parameterizations. Moreover, I've deep understanding of data structures and algorithms. Experience with software development on Linux open-source stack. Calculus, linear algebra and geometry related courses have been taken.

M.Phil. in Electronics

QAU, Pakistan Mar 2010 - Jun 2012

Department of Electronics, Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad, Pakistan.

• Thesis: "A Feature Based Algorithm for Automobile License Plate Detection and Recognition in Pakistan", Mar, 2012

- M.Phil. Supervisor: Prof Hasan Mahmood, Department of Electronics, QAU.
- · Research: Signal and Image Processing
- Grade: A

M.Sc. in Electronics QAU, Pakistan

Department of Electronics, Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad, Pakistan.

- 2nd position in batch
- · Projects: completed 9+ projects related to C++, Verilog/HDL and Micro-controller programming.

B.Sc. in Mathematics and Physics

BZU, Pakistan

Sep. 2005 - Aug. 2007

Sep 2007 - Jun 2010

Bahauddin Zakariya University, Multan Pakistan

• Grade: 1st Division

Honors & Awards

July, 2021	Educational Technology Innovation: Gold Award, The Teaching and Learning Innovation Expo, CUHK	CUHK, Hong Kong
July, 2021	Pedagogical Innovation: Silver Award, The Teaching and Learning Innovation Expo, CUHK	CUHK, Hong Kong
July, 2018	Best Student Paper Finalist Award , IEEE Int. Conf. on CYBER Technology in Automation, Control, and Intelligent Systems	Tianjin, Chind
May, 2018	Audience Award, Campus Challenge - Transportation, HKUST	HKUST, HF
Nov, 2017	Best Mapper Award, Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab, HKUST	Shenzhen, Chino
May, 2017	Completion Award, The Graduate Teaching Assistant Training, HKUST	HKUST, HF
Dec, 2016	Best External Award, Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab, HKUST	Shenzhen, Chind
Nov, 2016	Completion Award, Author Workshop, Elsevier Publishing Campus	HKUST, HR
Sep 2016	CCMS PhD Scholarship, Won Chief Minister Marit Scholarship (CCMS) scholarship award by Punjab Government (PEEF), Pakistan for pursuing my PhD studies at HKUST, HK	Lahore, Ph
Sep 2013	Participant, Painting for peace (Pakistan-India-Afghanistan) event, a part of the Harmony initiative	Islamabad, Pr
Apr 2013	Participant, Case Spark in business plan competition	Islamabad, Pr
Apr 2013	Participant, Case EPICA	Islamabad, Pk
Apr 2013	Participant, How to be a Better Playwright Workshop by PNCA and US Embassay Pakistan	Islamabad, Pk
Oct 2012	Participant, Punjab Youth Festival	Lahore, Pk
Oct 2011	Participant, Int'l Youth Conference and Festival	Islamabad, Pk
Sep 2011	Participant, Asian Youth Conference and Peace Festival	Lahore, Pk
Apr 2011	Completion Award, Acting and Directing Theater Workshop by PNCA and US Embassay Pakistan	Islamabad, Pr
Dec 2011	Participant, National Drama Festival	Islamabad, Pr
Dec 2010	Instuctor of short Course, PHP Web Development' at the Department of Electronics, QAU	Islamabad, Pr
Apr 2013	Completion Award, Running River Rafting course by Adventure Foundation of Pakistan	Mansehra, Pr
Apr 2013	Completion Award, Paragliding course by QAU Adventure Club	Islamabad, Pr
Dec 2008	Award of Honor, Finance Secretary of Electronics Student Society (ESS) at QAU	Islamabad, Pr

Presentation

Navigating Academia Research & Industry, ITCN Asia 2023

Pak-China Friendship Centre,

Islamabad Feb. 2023

Panelist

• 'I emphasize taking the voluntary initiative by the tech industry first. Companies should realize that they need academic involvement to grow at a swift pace. Most VPs of big companies belong to academia.

• 'In return, companies would at least solve their quality hiring problems. Usually, universities need more funding for R&D and IP filings, etc. In a broader view, both could get huge benefits.

Teaching and Learning Innovation Expo 2021

CUHK, Hong Kong

Posters Presentation

Jul. 2021

- 'Mixed Reality in Hands-On Learning of Robotics' by Xinyan Zhao, Sabrina Lam, M. Usman M. Bhutta, Darwin Lau and Jimmy Lee.
- 'Online Robotics Laboratory Framework for Interactive and Group Hands-On Learning' by Ken Hui, Ken Kwok, M. Usman M. Bhutta, Darwin Lau and Jimmy Lee.

IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems [IROS, 2020]

Las Vegas, USA

Presentor as author

Oct. 2020

• Introduced Smart-Inspect for the micro scale localization and classification of smartphone glass defects for industrial automation.

Technology Start-up Support Scheme for Universities (TSSSU)

HKUST, Hong Kong

Presenter as COO Lisee Technology Corporation Company Limited, Hong Kong.

Jan. 2019

• Introduced Lisee technology in front of selection committee panel and won TSSSU 2019-20 funding of the amount of HK\$300,000.

IEEE Int. Conf. on CYBER Technology in Automation, Control, and Intelligent Systems [IEEE-CYBER 2018]

Tianjin, China

Presentor as author Jul. 2018

• Introduced PCR-Pro for the estimation of information matrix and scale difference for pose graph SLAM.

IET-Young Professionals Exhibition and Competition (IET-YPEC) 2018

CityU, Hong Kong

Presenter as COO Lisee Technology Corporation Company Limited, Hong Kong.

Jul. 2018

• Introduced Lisee technology at IET-YPEC 2018.

Campus Challenge @ HKUST Transportation

HKUST, Hong Kong

Presenter as participent

May 2018

HKUST got 80+ proposals for this compeitions, and arranged a roadshow. My proposal got selected for the audiance award after getting maximum votes.

High Tech Innovation and Entrepreneurship

HKUST, Hong Kong

Presenter as Entrepreneur

Dec. 2017

• Introduced my study related to the flying cars.

World First Youth Robotics Developemnt Forum 2017

Shangri-La Shenzhen, China.

Presenter as author.

Nov. 2017

• Introduced my work related to multi-agent SLAM system.

Scientific Review Services and Academic Services

Journal Referee Services

TJS Peer Reviewer, The Journal of Supercomputing 2024

RA-L Peer Reviewer, IEEE Robotics and Automation Letter 2024, -23, -22

TC Peer Reviewer, IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics 2022

Conference Referee Services

IROSPeer Reviewer, IEEE/RSJ RA-L and International Conference on Robotics and Automation2024, 23, -21, -20, -18ICRAPeer Reviewer, IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Robotics and Automation2023, -22, -21, -20UF, USPoster Judge, UF/IFAS Agricultural and Biological Engineering Poster Symposium2024

Teaching Assistant Positions

HKUST, HK **Teaching Assistant**, EESM 5547 - Multimedia Signal Processing

Spr 2018 Fall 2018

HKUST, HK **Teaching Assistant**, ELEC4820 - Medical Imaging

HKUST, HK **Teaching Assistant**, ELEC 1010 - Electronic and Information Technology

Skills

Robotics and Computer Vision Ubuntu, ROS, PCL, Docker, Catkin, OpenCV, OpenGV, Ceres Solver, g2o, Libpointmatcher

Machine Learning / Deep Learning Jupyter, Pytorch, Tensorflow, Keras, CUDA, Cluster (Hipergator)

Programming Python, C/C++, Matlab, git, LaTeX, FPGA, Verilog, Slurm

Web mkdocs, Hugo, Jekyll, PHP, MYSQL

Languages English, Urdu

Research.

G: Google Scholar | ORCID iD: 0000-0002-3512-4279

Journal Publications

In-Sensor Visual Perception and Inference

Journal

Yanan Liu and Rui Fan and Jianglong Guo and Hepeng Ni and M. Usman Maqbool Bhutta 2023 Intelligent Computing

Robust mobile robot navigation in cluttered environments based on hybrid adaptive neuro-fuzzy inference and sensor fusion

Journal (**IF: 8.8+**)

Muhammad Husnain Haider, Zhonglai Wanga, Abdullah Aman Khan, Hub Ali, Hao Zheng, Shaban Usman, Rajesh Kumar, M. Usman Maqbool Bhutta, Pengpeng Zhi

Aug 2022

2022 Journal of King Saud University-Computer and Information Sciences.

MAFNet: Segmentation of Road Potholes with Multi-modal Attention Fusion Network for Journal (**IF: 5.3+**) **Autonomous Vehicles** Zhen Feng, Yanning Guo, Qing Liang, M. Usman Maqbool Bhutta, Hengli Wang, Ming Liu, and Aug 2022 Yuxiang Sun 2022 IEEE Transactions on Instrumentation & Measurement Why-So-Deep: Towards Boosting Previously Trained Models for Visual Place Recognition Journal (IF: 5.4+) M Usman Maqbool Bhutta*, Yuxiang Sun, Darwin Lau and Ming Liu Jan 2022 IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters (RA-L)/ICRA, 2022 Loop-box: Multi-Agent Direct SLAM Triggered by Single Loop Closure for Large Scale Journal (**IF: 11.7+**) Mapping M Usman Maqbool Bhutta*, Manohar Kuse, Rui Fan, Yanan Liu and Ming Liu Oct 2020 2022 IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics **Efficient Reset Design Techniques** Journal Paper Qamar, Zoha, Bushra Yaseen, and Usman Maqbool 2015 Published in Science International Lahore Conference Proceedings Autonomous Mobile Robot Navigation using Adaptive Neuro Fuzzy Inference System Conference Paper Muhammad Husnain Haider and Hub Ali and Abdullah Aman Khan and Hao Zheng and M. May 2022 Usman Maqbool Bhutta and Shaban Usman and Pengpeng Zhi and Zhonglai Wang 2022 International Conference On Innovations And Development Of Information Technologies And Robotics (IDITR), 2022 Scale-Adaptive Pothole Detection and Tracking from 3-D Road Point Clouds Conference Paper Wu, Rigen and Fan, Jiahe and Guo, Libo and Qiao, Lei and Bhutta, M. Usman Maqbool and Aug 2021 Hosking, Brett and Vityazev, Sergey and Fan, Rui 2021 IEEE International Conference on Imaging Systems and Techniques (IST), 2021 Smart-Inspect: Micro Scale Localization and Classification of Smart Phone Glass Defects Conference Paper for Industrial Automation M Usman Maqbool Bhutta*, Shoaib Aslam, Peng Yun, Jianhao JIAO and Ming Liu Oct 2020 IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS 2020) Multiple Lane Detection Algorithm Based on Optimised Dense Disparity Map Estimation Conference Paper Han Ma, Yixin Ma, Jianhao Jiao, M Usman Maqbool Bhutta, Mohammud Junaid Bocus, Lujia Dec 2018 Wang, Ming Liu and Rui Fan Accepted in IEEE International Conference on Imaging Systems and Techniques (IST 2018) PCR-Pro: 3D Sparse and Different Scale Point Clouds Registration and Robust Estimation Conference Paper of Information Matrix For Pose Graph SLAM M Usman Maqbool Bhutta* and Ming Liu Jul 2018 Presented in IEEE Int. Conf. on CYBER Technology in Automation, Control, and Intelligent Systems (IEEE-CYBER 2018), and won Best Student Paper Finalist Award. An intelligent approach for robust detection and recognition of multiple color and font Conference Paper styles automobiles license plates: A feature-based algorithm M Usman Magbool Bhutta*, Hasan Mahmood, and Haroon Malik Jan 2015 Published in IEEE International Conference on Audio, Language and Image Processing (ICALIP 2014). **Patent** Semi-Supervised Learning Approach for Smart Phone Glasses Defect Inspection Muhammad Usman Maqbool Bhutta, Jianhao Jiao, Peng Yun, Yuan Wang, Xuebin Sun, Ming Liu

US Patent Jan 2020 U.S. Provisional Patent Application No. 62/974,937, Filing Date 01/06/2020.

Automatic Surface Defect Detection System for Smart Phone Glass Based on Deep Learning

Yuan Wang, Jianhao Jiao, Peng Yun, Muhammad Usman Maqbool Bhutta, Xuebin Sun, Ming Liu

U.S. Provisional Patent Application No. 62/974,938, Filing Date 01/06/2020.

US Patent Jan 2020

5



Prof Henry Medeiros

Associate Professor · Director of Computer Vision and Sensing Systems (COVISS) Lab, Department of Agricultural and Biological Engineering University of Florida, FL, USA +1 (352) 294 6706

Prof Hafiz Malik

 $Professor \quad \cdot \quad \text{Director of Information Systems, Security, and Forensics (ISSF), Electrical and Computer Engineering , University of Michigan-Dearborn, MI, USA.}$

+1 (313) 593 5677

Postdoc Supervisor

hmedeiros@ufl.edu

Research Supervisor

hafiz@umich.edu